And now we want to create a new multi-former. Let's go ahead and do that.
이제 새 멀티포머를 하나 만들겠습니다. 바로 진행하죠.
This time let's call this animation curve and multi-former. Awesome.
이번에는 이걸 ‘Animation Curve Multi-Former’라고 부르죠. 좋습니다.
Save this and open this one. Assign sculptal mesh to be the skin.
저장하고 이걸 열어주세요. 스킨으로 사용할 스켈레탈 메시를 지정합니다.
And then animation sequence. Be the training data one and also the geometry cache.
그리고 애니메이션 시퀀스는 학습용 데이터로 쓰던 것을, 지오메트리 캐시도 함께 지정합니다.
Great. Now here it says needs inputs. Now remember this time we need to give the curves as inputs.
좋습니다. 여기 ‘입력이 필요하다’고 나오죠. 이번에는 커브들을 입력으로 넘겨줘야 한다는 점을 기억하세요.
So if you add all of the curves, they both should show up over here.
그래서 모든 커브를 추가하면 여기 둘 다 표시되어야 합니다.
It's 100 iterations. Over here, if you use the local mode, I think that's not working for the current 5.6 release.
여기 반복 횟수는 100입니다. 그리고 현재 5.6 릴리스에서는 로컬 모드를 사용하면 동작하지 않는 것으로 보입니다.
This is something we just fixed.
이 부분은 방금 수정되었습니다.
For 5.7 exactly, you should see the error message.
정확히 5.7부터는 오류 메시지가 표시될 겁니다.
So make sure you change that from local to global.
그러니 로컬이 아니라 글로벌로 바꿔주세요.
And then train model again.
그리고 모델을 다시 학습시킵니다.
You see the loss is going down. You can use more iterations if you want to, but for demonstration purpose.
보시다시피 손실 값이 내려가고 있습니다. 원한다면 반복 횟수를 더 늘릴 수 있지만 여기선 시연용으로만 진행하겠습니다.
Now you should also see an error message saying train neural network is incompatible with selected sculptal mesh.
이제 ‘선택한 스켈레탈 메시와 학습용 신경망이 호환되지 않는다’는 오류 메시지도 보일 겁니다.
If you open up the output log, it will show you that the bicep curve or the lower pec curve is missing.
출력 로그를 열어보면 이두근 커브 또는 하부 대흉근 커브가 빠져 있다고 나옵니다.
So let's go ahead and go to the sculptal mesh.
그럼 스켈레탈 메시로 가보겠습니다.
Then find the skeleton.
그리고 스켈레톤을 찾습니다.
That is right here.
여기 있네요.
And let's copy these curves.
이 커브들을 복사하겠습니다.
Then we can paste it here.
그다음 여기 붙여넣으면 됩니다.
Let's go.
좋아요, 진행하죠.
We save this.
이걸 저장합니다.
Go back to the former.
멀티포머 에셋으로 돌아가세요.
Close this one.
이 창을 닫고,
Train.
학습.
And then train again.
그리고 한 번 더 학습.
Now you should see that error message should be gone.
이제 그 오류 메시지가 사라졌을 겁니다.
That's because that multi-former right now only supports curves on the skeleton asset instead of the skeletal mesh asset.
그 이유는 현재 멀티포머가 스켈레탈 메시 에셋이 아니라 스켈레톤 에셋에 있는 커브만 지원하기 때문입니다.
I believe they're fixing this in the very next release.
다음 릴리스에서 이 부분이 수정될 예정으로 알고 있습니다.
So now we can start validating our training.
이제 학습 결과를 검증해 보겠습니다.
Let's go into testing.
테스트 탭으로 가보죠.
Then again, set the test animation to be exactly the same as training animation.
그리고 테스트용 애니메이션을 학습 때 사용한 것과 동일하게 설정합니다.
Just to see if the network fits.
네트워크가 잘 맞는지 확인하려는 목적입니다.
And we can turn on show heat map.
‘히트맵 표시’도 켭니다.
Now you can see where the delta is being applied.
이제 델타가 어디에 적용되는지 볼 수 있습니다.
So again, from 0 to 20, it's a bicep contraction.
다시 말해, 0~20 프레임 구간은 이두근 수축이고,
And then 20 to 40, it's a lower pec contraction.
20~40 프레임은 하부 대흉근 수축입니다.
Which means our network is fitting pretty good.
즉, 네트워크가 꽤 잘 맞고 있다는 뜻이죠.
Now let's use this curve driven a multi-former in blueprint example.
이제 이 커브 구동 멀티포머를 블루프린트 예제에서 사용해 보겠습니다.
Let's go back to the main level.
메인 레벨로 돌아가서,
And let's create a new level.
새 레벨을 하나 만들죠.
Okay.
네.
And then let's drag out our sculptor mesh, which is the skin.
그다음 스킨이 될 스켈레탈 메시 액터를 끌어다 놓습니다.
That's right here.
바로 여기 있네요.
Now let's make a blueprint out of this.
이걸 블루프린트로 만들어 보겠습니다.
So we can do this by convert selection to a blueprint class.
‘선택 항목을 블루프린트 클래스로 변환’을 사용하면 됩니다.
That's good.
좋아요.
Now there's our blueprint.
이제 블루프린트가 생겼습니다.
And over here, we can add a multi-former component.
여기에 멀티포머 컴포넌트를 추가합니다.
And what we can do is we can assign our multi-former asset.
그리고 방금 만든 멀티포머 에셋을 지정합니다.
This is assigned to be the one that we just created.
방금 생성한 그 에셋으로 연결하면 됩니다.
Okay.
네.
And over here, the sculptor mesh component.
그리고 이쪽 스켈레탈 메시 컴포넌트에는,
Let's use animation asset because eventually we're going to drive this using animation.
나중에 애니메이션으로 구동할 것이므로 ‘애니메이션 에셋 사용’으로 설정합시다.
So let's compile this for now.
일단 컴파일해 두고,
But over here, the eventual animation that we'll use will be a copy of the bicep curl animation.
여기서 사용할 애니메이션은 이두근 컬 애니메이션을 복제해 쓸 겁니다.
So let's duplicate that.
그래서 그걸 복제하죠.
We're going to call this slip weights, but with activation.
We're going to call this slip weights, but with activation.
Okay, let's save this.
Okay, let's save this.
And if we go back to the blueprint, we can assign this animation data.
And if we go back to the blueprint, we can assign this animation data.
You can see now it starts to play.
You can see now it starts to play.
Make sure we compile this.
Make sure we compile this.
Save this.
Save this.
Let's start adding some curves to the animation to drive independent muscle activation.
Let's start adding some curves to the animation to drive independent muscle activation.
Go to our animation over here, and then add curve here.
Go to our animation over here, and then add curve here.
Let's find our bicep.
Let's find our bicep.
And also the lower pec curve.
하부 대흉근 커브도 추가합니다.
There we go.
네,
Add them too.
이것들도 추가하세요.
We can open them up in the curve editor.
커브 에디터에서 열어볼 수 있습니다.
And let's start by adding a pulse to the bicep.
이두근 커브에 펄스를 하나 추가하는 것부터 시작하죠.
Add some keys to it.
키를 몇 개 더 찍어주고,
Another one.
하나 더,
So something in the middle.
중간에도 하나 넣습니다.
Now let's make it from 0 to 1.
이제 0에서 1로 오르게 만들고,
Approximately.
대략 이 정도로요.
Okay.
네.
Now we can save this.
이제 저장하고,
If we go back to our blueprint and wait for the start of the animation.
블루프린트로 돌아가 애니메이션 시작 타이밍을 기다리면,
There we go.
네,
We should see a quick contraction of the bicep.
이두근이 잠깐 수축하는 걸 볼 수 있을 겁니다.
And that's from the animation curve, actually.
사실 이건 애니메이션 커브에서 나온 동작이죠.
Okay.
네.
So let's actually refine that a little bit.
이걸 조금 더 다듬어 보겠습니다.
Back to our animation.
애니메이션으로 돌아가서,
Then start making some meaningful adjustments.
좀 더 의미 있는 조정을 해보죠.
Okay.
네.
The idea is that when we have the animation over here.
아이디어는 이렇습니다. 이 구간에서 애니메이션이 진행될 때,
Say when arm starts to contract.
이를테면 팔이 수축하기 시작하면,
Right there.
바로 여기죠.
We want some lower pec contraction.
하부 대흉근도 조금 수축하게 만들고 싶습니다.
Okay.
네.
So let's mark this as the starting point.
그럼 여기를 시작 지점으로 표시하고,
Add a key to it.
여기에 키를 하나 추가합니다.
And let's mark here to be...
그리고 여기는 ...로 표시하겠습니다.
Or over here to be the end of it.
또는 여기쯤을 끝 지점으로 잡겠습니다.
Then let's add a pulse.
Then let's add a pulse.
Alright.
Alright.
Let's also add some bicep contraction there.
Let's also add some bicep contraction there.
So let's say we start from here.
So let's say we start from here.
The bicep.
The bicep.
Let's delete the current ones first.
Let's delete the current ones first.
Say we're starting from here.
Say we're starting from here.
Add key.
Add key.
And then about here is the peak.
And then about here is the peak.
And here is the end.
여기가 끝 지점입니다.
Again, from 0 to 1 to 0.
다시 0에서 1로 올라갔다가 0으로 내려오는 형태죠.
So look at that.
자, 보세요.
Now we have...
이제 ...가 준비됐습니다.
Modify two curves.
두 개의 커브를 수정해서,
So that they should behave differently
첫 번째 이두근 컬 구간에서
in the very first bicep curl.
서로 다르게 동작하도록 했습니다.
So let's save this.
이제 저장하죠.
And go back to the blueprint.
그리고 블루프린트로 돌아갑니다.
Try to see the difference.
차이가 나는지 확인해봅시다.
Boom.
좋아요.
It starts.
시작됐습니다.
Zoom in a little bit.
조금 확대하고,
Wait for it to restart.
다시 시작할 때까지 잠깐 기다리면,
There you can see the lower pec is contracting.
여기서 하부 대흉근이 수축하는 걸 볼 수 있습니다.
Let's focus on the bicep this time.
이번에는 이두근에 집중해볼게요.
Start over.
처음부터 다시.
There.
여기.
See now we have a bicep contraction right there.
보이시죠? 방금 이두근 수축이 발생했습니다.
And that's how I want to show you
이렇게 해서 제가 보여드리고 싶었던 건,
how to control muscle activation independently.
근육 활성화를 서로 독립적으로 제어하는 방법입니다.
Besides the pose-driven ML deformer.
포즈 기반 ML 디포머와는 별개로요.
And I hope you enjoy this series.
이 시리즈가 도움이 되셨길 바랍니다.